Guide to the Asian Pacific American Labor Alliance (APALA) Records WAG.324
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Asian Pacific American Labor Alliance (APALA) Records
1970s-ongoing
1990-2010
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Asian Pacific American Labor Alliance
WAG.324
60 Linear Feet in 53 record cartons, 3 flat boxes, and 3 card boxes
41 videocassettes (digital betacam)
91 videocassettes (vhs)
7 videocassettes (u-matic)
5 videodiscs (dvd)
9 audiocassettes
2 sound discs (cd)
3 websites in 3 archived websites
Founded in 1992, the Asian Pacific American Labor Alliance (APALA) was created to address the continued underrepresentation of Asian Pacific American (APA) workers in the labor movement and the specific challenges APA workers face. The collection documents many of the activities of the national office and some of the local chapters of the APALA from its early years through 2009, as well as some of the activities of other APA organizations. Materials date from the 1970s through 2019, with the bulk of the material dating from 1992 to 2009. The collection includes paper and audiovisual materials regarding APALA annual conventions and events; meeting minutes; photographs of events; reports and audiovisual materials created by other APA groups; and archived versions of the APALA's websites and the Washington, DC chapter's website.
Historical Note
The foundations for the creation of the Asian Pacific American Labor Alliance (APALA) were laid in 1990 when a number of Asian Pacific American (APA) labor activists presented the AFL-CIO with a proposal to better address the continued underrepresentation of APA workers in the labor movement by forming a national APA labor organization. These activists sought to get more APA workers into unions, especially those working in historically important industries such as garment factories and restaurants. The APALA founders also recognized that, in addition to traditional workers' rights issues like fair wages and health care, APA workers face workplace discrimination and challenges related to immigration status, language ability, and education which force many Asian and Pacific Islander Americans into low-paying and insecure jobs.
In 1991, the Executive Council of the AFL-CIO formed a steering committee consisting of representatives from the three regional APA labor groups, representatives from Hawaii's AFL-CIO, and the seven founding unions to explore the rationales and practicalities of forming a national APA labor organization.
APALA became a formal entity at the National Founding Convention in 1992. Over 500 APA labor activists, representing major cities across the United States, gathered in Washington, D.C. APALA was envisioned as an organization that would address a number of pressing needs within the APA community by educating laborers, promoting political education and voter registration, and training and mentoring APA leaders within the labor movement and the greater community. In addition, it was decided that APALA would be committed to the defense and advocacy of civil and human rights of APA laborers, immigrants, and people of color, while developing ties to international labor organizations, especially those within the Asia-Pacific Rim.
With approximately 660,000 members, a national office in Washington, D.C., and 13 chapters and pre-chapters across the country, APALA remains the first and only national organization of APA union members.
Scope and Content Note
The Asian Pacific American Labor Alliance (APALA) Records document many of the activities of the national APALA office and some of its local chapters (especially the New York, San Francisco, Seattle, and Los Angeles chapters) from the organization's early years through 2009. The collection consists mostly of research and organizing materials related to APALA's various advocacy efforts in the areas of minority, immigrant, and/or workers' rights. Additionally, the APALA Records contain the activities of the executive board, convention materials, e-mail correspondence (especially correspondence written by or to Jin Sook Lee and Gloria T. Caoile, former Executive Directors of APALA) and materials related to various political and voter mobilization campaigns. The collection also includes photographic and audiovisual materials from APALA events and archived versions of the APALA's websites and the Washington, DC chapter's website. The websites include information about national and Washington chapter APALA events, programs, and political activities.
Parts of the collection also include materials generated by the Public Services Labor Independent Confederation (PSLINK), the union for government workers in the Philippines, and the American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (AFSCME), especially during Gloria Caoile's term as assistant to the AFSCME president. The collection also includes materials created by other APA organizations, particularly the National Council of Asian Pacific Americans (NCAPA), of which APALA is a member, and other labor groups, such as the Labor Coalition for Community Action. To a lesser extent, there are materials generated by other minority activist groups, such as the Coalition of Black Trade Unionists (CBTU).
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Related Materials
Papers related to the Asian Pacific American Labor Alliance can be found in the Rocky Chin Papers (WAG 325).
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor. Materials are described at the box level.
Separated Materials
Approximately twenty-five issues of the APALA News, three books, and some issues of Filipinas magazine were separated for library cataloging. Some personnel documents pertaining to employee finances and health insurance and/or containing sensitive information like Social Security numbers were removed. Personal materials were returned to the donors.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by the Asian Pacific American Labor Alliance (APALA) in March 2012. The accession number associated with this gift is 2012.020.
A small number of publications produced by the APALA were discovered in the repository and added to the collection in 2014. The accession number associated with these materials is 2014.034.
Custodial History
The archived website was migrated from the California Digital Library's Web Archiving Service to the Internet Archive's Archive-It Service in November 2015. The link to California Digital Library was removed in October 2017.
Websites were initially selected by curators and captured through the use of The California Digital Library's Web Archiving Service in 2007 as part of the Tamiment-Wagner: Labor Unions and Organizations (U.S.) Web Archive. In 2017, crawling of two of the websites, https://apalanet.wordpress.com/ and https://apaladc.wordpress.com/, was discontinued. In 2015, these websites were migrated to Archive-It. Archive-It uses web crawling technology to capture websites at a scheduled time and displays only an archived copy, from the resulting WARC file, of the website.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu, (212) 998-2630 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Born-digital materials have not been transferred and may not be available to researchers. Researchers may request access copies. To request that material be transferred, or if you are unsure if material has been transferred, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu, (212) 998-2630 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Due to technical or privacy issues, archived websites may not be exact copies of the original website at the time of the web crawl. Certain file types will not be captured dependent on how they are embedded in the site. Other parts of websites that the crawler has difficulty capturing includes Javascript, streaming content, database-driven content, and highly interactive content. Full-Text searches of archived websites are available at https://archive-it.org/organizations/567.
Take Down Policy
Archived websites are made accessible for purposes of education and research. NYU Libraries have given attribution to rights holders when possible; however, due to the nature of archival collections, we are not always able to identify this information.
If you hold the rights to materials in our archived websites that are unattributed, please let us know so that we may maintain accurate information about these materials.
If you are a rights holder and are concerned that you have found material on this website for which you have not granted permission (or is not covered by a copyright exception under US copyright laws), you may request the removal of the material from our site by submitting a notice, with the elements described below, to tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu.
Please include the following in your notice: Identification of the material that you believe to be infringing and information sufficient to permit us to locate the material; your contact information, such as an address, telephone number, and email address; a statement that you are the owner, or authorized to act on behalf of the owner, of an exclusive right that is allegedly infringed and that you have a good-faith belief that use of the material in the manner complained of is not authorized by the copyright owner, its agent, or the law; a statement that the information in the notification is accurate and made under penalty of perjury; and your physical or electronic signature. Upon receiving a notice that includes the details listed above, we will remove the allegedly infringing material from public view while we assess the issues identified in your notice.
Minorities -- Civil rights -- United States.; Asian Americans -- Politics and government.; Minorities -- Employment -- United States.; Asian Americans -- Social conditions.; Minorities -- Education.; Race discrimination -- United States.; Asian Americans -- Employment.; Asian Americans -- Civil rights.; Asian Americans -- Economic conditions.; Asian American labor union members.; Discrimination in employment -- United States.; Immigrants -- United States -- Civil rights.; President's Advisory Commission on Asian Americans and Pacific Islanders (U.S.); Asian Pacific American Labor Alliance; Labor Coalition for Community Action; National Council of Asian Pacific Americans; AFL-CIO; AFSCME; Asian Pacific American Labor Alliance
- Box 1, 1990-1993
  Scope and Content Note
  Betacam Tapes from APALA Events
- Box 2, 1993-1999, undated
  Betacam Tapes, Slides, and Cassette Tapes (from APALA Events and Unlabeled); "Women of Hope" Pamphlets; and Photographs and Negatives from Various Events, including: 1999 APALA Convention in Washington, DC, 1997 Convention in San Francisco, 1995 AFL-CIO Full Participation Conference, 1996 Fundraiser in San Francisco, and Labor Day 1998
- Box 3, 1990s-2004
  VHS Tapes of APALA Events and Programs Produced by Various Organizations
- Box 4, 1982, 1993-2001, undated
  Photographs, Negatives, and Slides from Various Events, including: 1993 APALA Convention in Los Angeles, 1994 Organizers Training, 1994 Education Conference in Seattle, 1995 Asian Labor Festival, 1995 Convention in New York City, and 1997 Convention in San Francisco
- Box 5, 1993-2010, undated
  Photographs (especially 1993 APALA Conference in Los Angeles); Four VHS Tapes; 1996 Conference Button; Promotional Materials; Voting Guides; and Reports and Organizing Materials re: National Politics, Building APALA Chapters, and the Asian Workforce in Washington, D.C.
- Box 6, 1993-2000
  Oversize Box: AFL-CIO Gavels; Three Plaques Presented to Gloria Caoile; Gloria Caoile Magnets; Medal from the Hubert H. Humphrey Institute of Public Affairs at the University of Minnesota; Delegate Nametags and Pins; Commemorative Coins from Philippine Republic Day Fiftieth Anniversary; and Pens, Keychains, and Other Ephemera from Various Labor and/or APA Groups
- Box 7, 1999-2007, undated
  "Communities at Work Toolbox" (AFL-CIO Guide to Defending Workers' Freedom to Form Unions) and Photographs of: APALA Ninth Biennial Convention, the 1999 Convention in Washington, DC, and Other Events
- Box 8, 1993-2004, undated
  Photographs, Negatives, Slides, and Contact Sheets of: 1995 APALA 101 Training in Los Angeles; 1999 Convention in Washington, DC; Labor Day 1998; 2004 Nevada Get Out the Vote; and Various Other APALA Events
- Box 9, 2002-2008
  APALA National Office Organizational Files from 2008 (Budgets, Convention Rosters, Correspondence, Events Publicity, Campaigns/Partnerships, etc.) and Voter Mobilization Campaigns, especially "Get Out the Vote"
- Box 10, 1994-2004, 2008, undated
  APALA National Office Organizational Files from 2008 and Photographs of: 1997 Convention in San Francisco, 1999 San Francisco Chapter Officers and Board Members, and Other People and Events
- Box 11, 1982, 1992-1995, 1997, 2000-2003
  Photographs from 1994 Education Conference in Seattle; Photographs and Contact Sheets from Various Other Events; National Council of Asian Pacific Americans (NCAPA) Meeting Minutes; and Materials from Various Conferences and Meetings on Asian Americans, Labor, Immigration, Political Education, and/or Feminism (early 2000s)
- Box 12, 1992-2000
  Materials from Conferences on Asian Americans, Labor, Immigrants, and/or Civil Rights; Research on Bilingual Programs for Limited-English Proficient (LEP) Students and the Federal Minimum Wage
- Box 13, 1990s-2003
  Convention Planning Materials and Research/Campaigns re: Gay and Lesbian Issues, Health Care, LEP Education, the Americans with Disabilities Act, Affirmative Action, Employment Discrimination, and the 2000 Census
- Box 14, 1995-2001
  Convention Planning Materials and Ballots
- Box 15, 2000-2010
  Oversize Box: APALA Tote Bags, Fans With Voter Information, Four DVDs, Two Floppy Disks, APIA Voter Mobilization Posters, Filipino American Voter Involvement Project Booklet, 2010 Peace Calendar, and Several Editions of Various Nevada APA Newspapers
- Box 16, 1990s-2001
  VHS, Betacam, and Ampex Tapes of APALA Events and Programs Produced by Various Organizations
- Box 17, 1990-2002, undated
  Photographs and VHS Tapes from Various Events; Asians in the Workforce and the Arts: A Photo Essay by Lia Chang; National Directory of Asian Pacific American Organizations (1995); and Business Cards and Miscellaneous Ephemera
- Box 18, 1990s-2003
  Barbara Grutter v. Lee Bollinger et al. and Kimberly James et al.; Political and Conference Buttons and Pins; and Research, Campaigns, and Jin Sook Lee E-mail Correspondence re: China and the World Trade Organization, Immigration, and Homeland Security
- Box 19, 1995-2004
  Statistics from the U.S. Bureau of the Census; Event Planning Materials; and Research, Campaigns, and Jin Sook Lee E-mail Correspondence re: Low Wage Immigrant Workers, Hate Crimes, Student Adjustment/DREAM Act, Workers' Rights in China/China and the WTO, Filipino World War II Veterans, Affirmative Action, APA Women Workers, and Voter Mobilization
- Box 20, 1997-2009
  Oversize Box: Two Floppy Disks from 1997 Convention in San Francisco, Picture CD, Several Oversize Photographs, APALA T-shirts, Form Mailings re: Immigration, and Stickers
- Box 21, 1996-2007
  Convention Packets (Agendas, Notes, and Reports/Memos), especially from the Leadership Conference on Civil Rights and APALA Executive Board; Chapter Files: Seattle, South Puget Sound, Los Angeles, and Washington, D.C.
- Box 22, 1989-2004, undated
  Chapter Files; Convention Materials; Election Ballots; and Gloria Caoile's AFSCME and Public Services Labor Independent Confederation (PSLINK) Reports on Women and/or Unionism in the Philippines ("Gloria" materials begin after ballots)
- Box 23, 1993-2003, undated
  Campaigns of Various APA Organizations and Gloria Caoile's AFSCME and Public Services Labor Independent Confederation (PSLINK) Materials (mainly Conferences and Reports on Women and/or Unionism in the Philippines) ("Gloria" papers end after "gender sensitive")
- Box 24, 2000s
  Campaigns of Various APA, Labor, and Minority Organizations and APA Voter Mobilization Campaigns
- Box 25, 2000s
  APA Voter Mobilization Campaigns and Labor Coalition for Community Action (LCCA): Meeting Minutes, Financial Documents, and Project Reports
- Box 26, 1996-2000s
  APA Voter Mobilization Campaigns, National Council of Asian Pacific Americans (NCAPA), and Articles and Reports re: Immigration, Hate Crimes, Hoffman Plastic Compounds v. NLRB, and Civil Liberties/Anti-Terrorism
- Box 27, 1998-2008
  National Council of Asian Pacific Americans (NCAPA) and Other APA Groups; APALA and AFL-CIO Political Activism (Various Campaigns, Projects, and Meetings)
- Box 28, 2000s
  APALA Political Activism (mainly "Get Out the Vote") and 2001 National Convention Materials
- Box 29, 2001-2004
  2001 APALA National Convention Materials and APALA Participation at Various Conferences/Meetings
- Box 30, 2000s
  APALA Participation at Various Conferences/Meetings and APALA Executive Board Meetings
- Box 31, 2000s
  APALA Executive Board Meetings; APALA Programming and Organizing Materials; and Voter Mobilization and Education Materials for Various National and Local Elections
- Box 32, 2000s
  Voter Mobilization for 2008 Presidential Primary in Philadelphia County; APALA Executive Board Meetings; and APALA Delegation to South Korea
- Box 33, 1994-2001, undated
  Working Copy of San Francisco 1997 Convention Banquet Booklet and Photographs, Negatives, and Contact Sheets from APALA Events, including: Asia Labor Festival, 1995 Convention in NYC, and Various Organizer Trainings
- Box 34, 2000s
  Regional Chapter Files (Alameda, Hawaii, Oakland, New York, San Diego, Portland/Oregon, and San Francisco) and National Files re: Starting Chapters
- Box 35, 1995-1997, 2007
  Convention Materials (NYC 1995 and San Francisco 1997) and Public Services International (PSI) Information on Socio-Political and Economic Situation in the Philippines (with Gloria Caoile's notes)
- Box 36, 2000s
  Asian Pacific Islander American National Demographics and Workforce Statistics, APALA Voter Mobilization Campaigns, Nonprofit Setup Materials, and Gloria Caoile Papers: Public Services International (PSI) Information on Socio-Political and Economic Situation in the Philippines, Human/Workers' Rights and Voter Mobilization Campaigns for Filipinos, Immigration Reform Advocacy, and the Employee Free Choice Act of 2007
- Box 37, 1997-2000s
  Administrative Files and Research Files: Food Stamps, Comprehensive Immigration Reform, Bill Lann Lee, and Hate Crimes
- Box 38, 1997-2000s
  Election Reform and Low Wage Immigrant Workers Advocacy; Programs from Philippine Independence Festivals; and Research Files: Health Care, Los Almos "Spy" Case, Daewoo Union Strike, Immigration, John Ashcroft, Affirmative Action, and Labor and Human Rights in the Mariana Islands
- Box 39, 1994-2005, undated
  President's Advisory Commission on Asian Americans and Pacific Islanders; 1994-1995 Convention Materials; and VHS Tapes (Speeches from Various Events and Programs on Immigrant Workers)
- Box 40, 1993-1995, 1997, 2006
  1993-1995 and 1997 Convention Materials and 2006 National Constitution
- Box 41, circa 1992-2009
  Kent Wong and Matt Finucane Speeches; Executive Board Meetings; and Research and Advocacy re: Voter Mobilization, Affirmative Action, Workers' Rights in China, Native Hawaiians, and Women and Minorities in Union Leadership
- Box 42, 1998-2009
  Executive Board Meetings and 2007 Convention Materials
- Box 43, circa 1992-2004, undated
  Photographs, Negatives, and Contact Sheets for Newsletters and from Various Events, including: 2004 Get Out the Vote, the APALA Founding Convention, Executive Board Meetings, and the New York Labor Festival
- Box 44, 1997-2000s
  Membership Files and Executive Board: Meetings, Mailings, and Members' Biographical Information
- Box 45, late 1990s-2005
  Convention Materials (mostly Administrative), Voter Mobilization Materials, and Reports on Asian American and Pacific Islander Population in the U.S. Created by Various APA Groups
- Box 46, 1998-2000s
  Personnel Files; Student Outreach Materials; Chapter Files; Get Out the Vote Funding; and APALA Organizer Training and Organizing Institute, AFL-CIO Materials
- Box 47, 1992-2009
  Nine Cassette Tapes; Two CDs; VHS Tape on Native Hawaiians; AFL-CIO Papers: Organizing Materials/APALA Partnership, Political Reports, and Martin Luther King, Jr. Observances; Reports on APA Population; and Gloria Caoile Papers: Voter Mobilization Materials
- Box 48, 1970s-early 2000s
  Gloria Caoile Papers: Voter Mobilization Materials, Speeches Given by Caoile, Awards Given to Caoile, Coalition of Black Trade Unionists 1999 Convention, and AFSCME Administrative and Personnel Files
- Box 49, late 1980s-2006
  APALA Executive Board: Meetings and Mailings; Gloria Caoile Papers: National Asian Pacific American Legal Consortium Census 2000 Education Project and Caoile's Appointment to President's Advisory Commission on Asian Americans and Pacific Islanders
- Box 50, 1996-2005
  Executive Board Meetings and 2003 Convention Materials
- Box 51, 1992-2000s
  APALA Convention Materials, including Founding Convention Programs
- Box 52, 2000s
  APALA Convention Materials (especially 2005 Convention), Research and Advocacy re: Labor in South Korea, and National Coalition for Asian Pacific Americans: Minutes, E-mail Correspondence, and Various Advocacy Issues
- Photographs, undated (Box 53, Box 54, Box 58)
- Unprocessed, APALA contract, Carolyn Fair, 32 Gigabytes (Box Shared Tamiment 064)
- Ephemera, Undated (Box 55, Box 57)
  Scope and Contents
  These boxes contain ephemera from APALA conventions, United States national elections, and labor union campaigns. Formats include buttons, balloons, business cards, and pens.
- Box 56, Undated
  VHS Tapes, Betacam, and Ampex Tapes containing speeches from various events and programs on immigrant workers, APALA events, and programs produced by various organizations.
- Archived Website, September 2007-ongoing; 1 websites in 1 archived website (E-records Electronic Records, E-records https://wayback.archive-it.org/6349/*/https://www.apalanet.org/, E-records https://wayback.archive-it.org/6349/*/https://apaladc.wordpress.com/, E-records https://wayback.archive-it.org/6349/*/https://apalanet.wordpress.com/)
  Founded in 1992, the Asian Pacific American Labor Alliance (APALA) was created to address the continued under-representation of Asian Pacific American (APA) workers in the labor movement and the specific challenges APA workers face. APALA works on projects related to voter registration, the DREAM Act, and workplace organizing. The website contains information on their executive board, youth leadership and organizing committees, press releases, news listings, convention information, and a blog.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements